let set10 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. The term Municipal Solid Waste (MSW) is generally used to describe:`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Wastes from industrial processes, construction and demolition debris.',
                    'B. Wastes from Private homes, commercial establishments and institutions.',
                    'C. Mining wastes',
                    'D. Agricultural wastes',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: B Municipal Solid Waste, also called garbage or trash, is nonhazardous disposable materials generated by households, institutions, industries, agriculture, and sewage. It is made up of waste, organics, and recyclable materials, with the municipality overseeing its disposal. Typically, municipal solid waste is collected, sperate and sent to either a landfill or municipal recycling center for processing. Municipal solid waste may contain a variety of pathogens, a source of which is often disposable diapers—it has been found that as many as 10% of the fecally soiled disposable diapers entering landfills contain enteroviruses. Another primary source of pathogens is sewage biosolids, where codisposal is practiced. Pathogens may also be present in domestic pet waste (e.g., cat litter) and food wastes. Municipal solid wastes from households have been found to average 7.7 × 108 coliforms and 4.7 × 108 fecal coliforms per gram. Salmonella have also been detected in domestic solid waste. In unlined landfills, such pathogens may be present in the leachate beneath landfills. Municipal solid waste represents a major crisis for rural communities because of the lack of awareness of the effects of people dumping their waste in the water canals causing water pollution as well as visual pollution. Others might burn the MSW in the streets causing air pollution as well as visual pollution. The municipal solid waste consists of organic waste, waste paper, plastic waste, tin cans, aluminum cans, textile, glass, etc. as discussed in Chapter 5. It is always recommended to establish a transfer station in rural communities because of low quantity. The transfer station consists of a conveyer belt for sorting, a hydraulic press for compacting paper, tin cans, textile, etc., and a ball mill to crush glass waste. It is always recommended to establish centralized recycling facilities among a number of rural communities.`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. What is true about Aerobic bacteria?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Flourish in the presence of free oxygen',
                    'B. Consume organic matter as their food',
                    'C. Oxidise organic matter in sewage',
                    'D. All',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: D An aerobic organism or aerobe is an organism that can survive and grow in an oxygenated environment. In contrast, an anaerobic organism (anaerobe) is any organism that does not require oxygen for growth. Some anaerobes react negatively or even die if oxygen is present.`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. Which of the following can be found as pollutants in the drinking water in some parts of India? \n 1. Arsenic \n 2. Sorbitol \n 3. Fluoride \n 4. Formaldehyde \n 5. Uranium \n Select the correct answer using the codes given below.`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. 1 and 3 only',
                    'B. 2, 4 and 5 only',
                    'C. 1, 3 and 5 only',
                    'D. 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: C  The easiest option is 3) Fluoride. So, (b) can be eliminated.  The next easiest option is Arsenic (Heavy metal). Damn!  Nest easiest option is Uranium. Many columns are written on uranium mining and its ill-effects. So, (a) also can be elevated. (a) and (b) eliminated. (c) and (d) remains.  The knowledge of either “Sorbitol” or “Formaldehyde” will tell us the answer.  Formaldehyde is more known than sorbitol. Googling didn’t give me any authentic source that called formaldehyde a water pollutant. It is used as a preservative to preserve human organs. It finds some application in textile, resigns and wood industry.  Sorbitol (glucitol) is a sugar alcohol with a sweet taste which the human body metabolises slowly.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. With reference to sources of water pollution, which of the following is/are true? \n 1. Natural sources \n 2. Domestic sources \n 3. Agricultural sources \n 4. Industrial sources \n Select the correct answer from the following codes`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Only 4',
                    'B. Only 2, 3 and 4',
                    'C. Only 3 and 4',
                    'D. 1, 2, 3 and',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: D Water pollution is caused by a variety of human activities such as industrial, agricultural and domestic and also by natural sources. Natural sources of pollution of water are soil erosion, leaching of minerals from rocks and decaying of organic matter.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. Which of the following pairs are correctly matched? Pollutant Disease \n 1. Arsenic Skin Cancer \n 2. Lead Itai - Itai \n 3. Cadmium displexia \n Select the correct answer from the following codes`,
            options:
                [
                    'a. Only 1',
                    'b. Only 1 and 2',
                    'c. Only 2 and 3',
                    'd. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: D Pollution of water bodies by mercury causes Minamata`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. With reference to Eutrophication, Which of the following is/are true? \n 1. It is phenomenon of nutrient enrichment of a water body \n 2. It depletes the water of dissolved oxygen (DO). \n 3. Human activities are mainly responsible for the eutrophication \n Select the correct answer from the following codes`,
            options:
                [
                    'a. Only 1',
                    'b. Only 1 and 2',
                    'c. Only 2 and 3',
                    'd. 1, 2 and 3',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: D Discharge of domestic waste, agricultural surface runoff, land drainage and industrial effluents in a water body leads to rapid nutrients enrichment in a water body. The excessive nutrient enrichment in a water body encourages the growth of algae, water hyacinth, Phytoplankton and other aquatic plants. The biological demand for oxygen (BOD) increases with the increase in aquatic organisms.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. What minerals are found in the run-off from agricultural land and treated and untreated sewage effluents, which are highly responsible for eutrophication of water bodies?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Phosphorous and carbon',
                    'B. Nitrogen and phosphorus',
                    'C. Potassium and arsenic',
                    'D. Iron and manganese',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: B Eutrophication occurs when fresh water is artificially supplemented with nutrients, which causes an abnormal plant growth. The output of waste into the water bodies from industries, agriculture, and urban communities generally exceeds the biological capacities of aquatic systems. Runoff of chemical fertilizers from fields is a major cause. When organic matter exceeds the capacity of those microorganisms in water that break it down and recycle it, it encourages rapid growth, or blooms of algae. When they die, remains of the dead algae add further to the organic wastes already in water; eventually, water becomes deficient in oxygen.`
        },
        {
            question: `#8. The GAP (Ganga Action Plan) - a project to clean up the polluted waters of the Ganga - plans to intercept and divert municipal sewage falling into the river from 25 large urban conglomerates in thee states.`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. UP, Haryana and Punjab',
                    'B. UP, Bihar and West Bengal',
                    'C. Himachal Pradesh, UP, and Haryana',
                    'D. Orissa , Bihar and West Bengal',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: B Realizing the magnitude of the problem with regard to the pollution of the river Ganga, Government of India launched the Ganga Action Plan in 1985 to clean this holy river. This was the first time that the problem of water pollution was being tackled at a national level with interest being shown by all. It effectively functions in three states - Uttar Pradesh, Bengal, and Bihar - the three states through which it flows. Though there has been some change in the water quality of the river since this programme began, the improvement is very marginal and is far below the expected rate. Work on this project is still underway and it is yet to be seen whether they will be able to achieve their target.`
        },
        {
            question: `#9. Wetlands are very rich and diverse ecosystems. Of the wetlands of international importance in the world, a large number are subject to moderate or high threat. Which convention signed in Iran protects this specific ecosystem (wetlands) on a global basis?`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. The Vienna Convention',
                    'B. The Ramsar Convention',
                    'C. The Basel Convention',
                    'D. None',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: B Wetlands are areas lying along the banks of rivers and lakes, and coastal regions. They are life-supporting systems providing fish, forest products, water, flood control, erosion buffering, a plant gene pool, wildlife, recreation, and tourism areas. Though they are endowed with a rich biodiversity yet of late, they are being greatly exploited. A number of factors have been responsible for the depletion of wetland areas mainly the mangrove forests, along the coasts of India. Intensive aquacultural development, deforestation, pollution from tankers, domestic waste, agricultural run off, and industrial effluents are some of the factors. In 1981, Chilika Lake, India's largest brackish water lagoon, was the first site to be designated a Ramsar Wetland of International Importance.`
        },
        {
            question: `#10. In a survey recently conducted by the CGWA (Central Ground Water Authority) and CPCB (Central Pollution Control Board), the groundwater samples in one-fourth of the neighborhood tested in New Delhi were unfit for drinking. They contained high levels of two minerals that are not eliminated by ordinary water filters and are extremely harmful at high concentrations.`,
            options:
                [
                    'A. Mercury and zinc',
                    'B. Fluoride and arsenic',
                    'C. Nitrate and fluoride',
                    'D. Aesenic and lead',
                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: Answer: A Answer: A`
        },
        {
            question:`11. Which sector is the single-largest consumer of fresh water in India?`,
            options:
            ['A. Industry',
            'B. Power',
            'C. Domestic',
            'D. Agriculture',
            ],
            answer:`Answer: D`,
            exp:`Answer: D
            Explanation: In a country like India where more than 50% of the
            population is rural-based, agriculture is one of the most important
            professions. The fields have to be regularly watered and there are
            large networks of irrigation systems all over the country. This
            sector is therefore the largest consumer of water in the country. In
            the past few years, various methods have been introduced to
            decrease the wastage of water in this sector. One of the methods
            that is becoming popular is that of drip irrigation.`
        }
    ]